Guide to the Trent history of medicine manuscripts collection, [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Trent History of Medicine manuscript collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980, (780 collections; approximately 6,000 items)
  - Drake, Benjamin, 1794-1841. Letter, 1838, Oct. 29, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Letter (ALS). Drake's resignation from appointment as surgeon and as treasurer of the Ophthalmic Dispensary. Verso of letter bears an anonymous reply, dated the same day, on behalf of the recipients, the acting executive committee of the board of trustees, stating that they must return the resignation since they are not empowered to appoint or remove officers.
  - Drake, Daniel, 1785-1852. Letter, 1838, Oct. 29, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Physician and medical professor. Papers consist of Drake's professional and personal correspondence. His correspondents include the Philadelphia physician, John Vaughan, to whom he recommends the chemist Robert Best; General Zachary Taylor; Kentucky Governor Robert Perkins Letcher, to whom he recommends Bishop B.B. Smith as Superintendent of Public Instruction; Coleman Rogers, with whom he had a personal disagreement; a patient, Mrs. Davis; and his grandson, Josiah C. Drake.
  - Draper, John William, 1811-1882. Letter, [Between 1840 and 1882, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Physician, chemist and professor. Letter (ALS). Writes of the reception of one of his books.
  - Dreys, Laure. Letter, 1887, Jan. 2, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Letter (ALS). Relates the circumstances of Dreys' visit to Paris, namely the death of his sister, widow of Dr. Alphonse Sanson. Informs Blanche of a visit to M. Kaempfen in Paris. Asks Blanche to convey his gratitude to "le Directeur" for granting him leave to attend to the funeral. The letter also bears a note (ANS), dated 1887. Jan. 22, from E. Blanche, Auteuil, to "confrère et ami", presumably forwarding Dreys' letter to "le Directeur".
  - Dubois, A. Note, 1843, July 8, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Note (ANS). Announces his safe arrival and requests that a prescription which he had forgotten be sent.
  - Dubois, Antoine, 1756-1837. Papers, 1821-1826, (3 items) (Box 4)
    French surgeon, anatomist, and accoucheur. Three notes (ANS). One note informs a M. Cochin of his intent to visit Mme Benoit and to accept M. Benoit's offer of transportation. M. Benoit is identified as Cochin's father-in-law.
  - Dubos, René Jules, 1901-1982. Letter, 1948, July 1, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Bacteriologist and 1969 Pulitzer Prize winner. Letter (TLS) relating to Elberg's contribution to the text, "Bacterial and mycotic infections of man".
  - Duchenne, Guillaume-Benjamin, 1806-1875. Papers, 1874, Feb. 18-Nov. 22, (2 items) (Box 4)
    Self-educated French pathologist and founder of modern electrotherapeutic methods. Note (ANS) and letter (ALS). Duchenne relates the case history of a Mr. C., a patient with Parkinson's disease, and his treatment with electrotherapy.
  - Dudley, Benjamin Winslow, 1785-1870. Papers, 1841-1870, (2 items) (Box 4)
    U.S. surgeon. Letters (ALS) dated 28 March 1841 in which Dudley recommends Jos. H. Bledsoe to President W. H. Harrison; newspaper clipping of Dudley's obituary.
  - Dujardin-Beaumetz, 1833-1895. Letter, [Between 1852 and 1895], (1 item) (Box 4)
    Parisian physician. Letter (ALS). Asks that recipient examine bearer of letter. Typed transcription available.
  - Duméril, Auguste Henri André, 1812-1870. Note, 1854, (1 item) (Box 4)
    French physician. Note (ANS). Duméril recommends a M. Albanel to the addressee.
  - Duncan, Andrew, 1773-1832. Letter, [Between 1793 and 1832], (1 item) (Box 4)
    Scots physician. Letter (ALS). Invites addressee to join the Horticulture Society [of Edinburgh].
  - Duncan, G. Postcard, 1855, Aug. 20, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Postcard signed. Thanks Fraenkel in haste.
  - Duncan, James Matthews, 1826-1890. Note, [Between 1846 and 1890], (1 item) (Box 4)
    Scots gynecologist and pediatrician. Note (ANS). Regretfully declines invitation.
  - Dunglison, Robley, 1798-1869. Papers, 1852-1859, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Professor and dean of the Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia. Two letters (ALS). In a letter to the New York printer and publisher Justus Starr Redfield, Dunglison writes regarding his biography in Men of the Times and about the use of burnt sponge in the treatment of goitre. He refers to various people and affairs at the Jefferson Medical College. The treatment of goitre is also the subject of his letter to Henry Randall.
  - Dupuytren, Guillaume, 1777-1835. Letter, 1819, Apr. 1, (1 item) (Box 4)
    French surgeon, pathologist and anatomist. Letter (ALS). Recommends Edmond Marx for the position of intern at the Hotel Dieu.
  - Durant, Edward. Document, 1776, June 22, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Surgeon in Col. Josiah Whitney's Regiment. Holograph, signed. Attests that he will use medicines received of Dr. John Greenleaf in accordance with the resolves of the General Court of Mass.
  - Dutrochet, Henri, 1776-1847. Letter, 1838, May 26, (1 item) (Box 4)
    French physiologist. Letter (ALS). English translation available. Informs Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire that his present research relates to the heat generated by plants. Dutrochet measures this energy with a thermo-galvanometer, which Becquerel has taught him to use. Thanks Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire for informing him about recent events at the Academy and hopes that such inappropriate scenes will not recur, as they are detrimental to the reputation of the Academy. Comments upon the possible confirmation of the theory that swallows hibernate.
  - Earle, Pliny, 1809-1892. Papers, 1806-1897, (71 items) (Box 4)
    Quaker physician and alienist of Northhampton, Mass. Business and professional correspondence of Pliny Earle, Sr. (1762-1832), inventor and cotton textiles manufacturer, and of son Pliny Earle (1809-1892), physician and alienist, including a few personal letters to Miss Earle. Correspondence addressed to Earle, Sr., touches on politics, patent rights and carding machines. Correspondence addressed to Earle relates to mental illness and the institutional care of the mentally ill. He received letters from physicians, institutional administrators, and philanthropists, including a number of letters of introduction. Items, mostly letters (ALS) and 10 addressed envelopes, are arranged in roughly chronological order.
  - Eastlake, Charles Lock, Sir, 1793-1865. Letter, 1859, Feb. 7, (1 item) (Box 4)
    English painter and keeper of the National Gallery. Letter (ALS). Eastlake thanks Moore for his gift to the National Gallery of a portrait of Edward Jenner.
  - Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842. Papers, 1827-1831, (3 items) (Box 4)
    Botanist, geologist and professor at the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute. Letter (ALS) from William Tully informs Eaton that Stephen Van Rensselaer is at home. Eaton responds with a letter (ALS) to Van Rensselaer informing him of what his sons will need to bring if they are to accompany his expedition. In a later letter (ALS) Ebenezer Emmons solicits Eaton's editorial advice for the second edition of his "Manual of mineralogy and geology".
  - Eberle, John, 1787-1838. Letter, 1826, Mar. 1, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Physician and professor at Jefferson Medical College. Letter (ALS). Recommends a Mr. Dodd to James Buchanan, Esq.
  - Edward Augustus, Prince, Duke of Kent, 1767-1820. Letter, 1819, Aug. 2, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Father of Queen Victoria. LS. A letter relating to the Duke's business affairs, in which mention is made of the vaccination of "our little Victoria".
  - Ehrmann, Johann Christian, 1749-1827. Papers, 1792-1805, (8 items) (Box 4)
    German military physician in Frankfurt am Main. Papers are in German and in French. Michel-Augustin Thouret acknowledges receipt of a box of medical instruments. Other material relates to Ehrmann in his capacity as military physician. An autograph certificate, signed by Ehrmann, protests the treatment of the French dead, citing his own futile efforts to obtain a death certificate for a French grenadier. This document was promptly returned, accompanied by a note from his supervisor informing him that it could not be submitted to the minister in its present form.
  - Einhorn, Max, 1862-1953. Letters, 1943-1953, (4 items) (Box 4)
    Russian-born American physician. Two notes (ANS) from Einhorn to Goldstein, two letters (ALS) from Anne Koerber to Goldstein. Letters relate to Goldstein's efforts to obtain biographical information regarding Einhorn, as well as copies of his written work.
  - Eiselsberg, Anton, Freiherr von, 1860-1939. Letter, 1924, June 3, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Austrian surgeon. Letter (TLS). Thanks colleague for invitation to attend a conference, but regretfully informs him that he will not be able to attend.
  - Elwyn, Alfred Langdon, 1804-1884. Letter, 1859, May 18, (2 items) (Box 4)
    Physician and father-in-law of S. Weir Mitchell. Letters (ALS). Sends Mrs. Allen of Providence, an autograph collector, an autograph of financier Robert Morris. Writes of Morris' disastrous land speculations.
  - Emerson, Gouverneur, 1796-1874. Papers, 1847, (2 items) (Box 4)
    Physician and agriculturalist of Philadelphia. Two letters (ALS). Emerson sends additions to Mrs. Allen's collection and gives brief biographical synopses of each person, including Judge Hopkinson, Dr. Physick, Mathew Carey, Dr. Morton, Dr. Rush and Stephen Girard.
  - Emmet, Robert, 1729-1802. Letter, 1782, Dec. 27, (2 items) (Box 4)
    Physician of Dublin. Letters (ALS). Advises Mr. White, the suitor of a young lady in Emmet's care, that her father is strongly opposed to the match.
  - Emmet, Thomas Addis, 1828-1919. Letter, 1868, July 14, (1 item) (Box 4)
    U.S. obstetrician and gynecologist. Letter (ALS). Writes on the formation of stones after operations for vesico-vaginal fistula.
  - Engelmann, George, 1809-1884. Letter, 1843, Nov. 30, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Botanist and professor at Washington University. Letter (ALS). Writes of the successful collection efforts of botanists travelling with Oregon emigrants and with a mission of Jesuits.
  - Esquirol, Etienne, 1772-1840. Document, 1827, Oct. 3, (1 item) (Box 4)
    French psychiatrist. Holograph, signed. Attests to the state of mental health of a patient of the "Maison royale de Charenton".
  - Eustachius, Bartolomeus, d. 1574. Letter, circa 1565, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Bartolomeo Eustachi, Italian physician, one of the founders of science of human anatomy; prepared one of the first series of copper-engraved anatomical illustrations. Photostat of a letter (ALS).
  - Eustis, William, 1753-1825. Letter, 1812, June 6, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Army physician, politician and diplomat. Letter (ALS). Details efforts to increase the size of the army and to improve the efficiency of the military organization in preparation for a war with Great Britain. He also transcribes a copy of a letter received from Alexander Smyth, on recruiting measures.
  - Eve, Paul Fitzsimmons, 1806-1877. Autograph, undated, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Physician and professor of Georgia. End fragment of a letter (ALS).
  - Ewart, James Cossar, 1851-1933. Note, [Between 1870 and 1933], (1 item) (Box 4)
    Sottish anatomist and professor of natural history. Note (ANS).
  - Faure, Jean-Louis, 1863-1944. Papers, 1922, Mar., (2 items) (Box 4)
    French surgeon. Two AMS concerning techniques of heart surgery.
  - Fayrer, Joseph, Sir, 1824-1907. Papers, 1882-1900, (5 items) (Box 4)
    English physician and writer on tropical diseases. Includes a letter to Edward John Waring; Morell Mackenzie's letter to Fayrer; and a newspaper clipping of a review of Fayrer's book Recollections of my Life.
  - Fechner, Gustav Theodor, 1801-1887. Postcard, 1800, (1 item) (Box 4)
    German experimental psychologist, professor of physics at Leipzig. Autograph postcard, signed. Cancels appointment.
  - Féréol, Louis Félix Henri Second, d. 1891. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 4)
    French physician. Letter (ALS).
  - Ferguson, William, 1820-1887. Letter, 1854, Nov. 10, (1 item) (Box 4)
    English botanist and entomologist. Letter (ALS). Incidental.
  - Fergusson, William, Sir, 1808-1877. Papers, 1857-1865, (2 items) (Box 4)
    British surgeon. Two letters (ALS) of a casual nature.
  - Ferrier, David, 1843-1928. Note, 1891, June 20, (1 item) (Box 4)
    British neuropathologist. Note (ANS). Relates to a memorandum on the case of a patient.
  - Ferrus, Guillaume-Marie-André, 1784-1861. Letter [Between 1800 and 1826?], June 16, (1 item) (Box 4)
    French psychiatrist and student of Philippe Pinel. Letter (ALS). Inquires on behalf of Charles Pinel regarding a bust of his father, Philippe Pinel.
  - Finley, James Bradley, 1781-1856. Letter, 1802, May 14, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Physician and Methodist preacher of North Carolina. Letter (ALS). Introduces Colonel Burr.
  - Finsen, Niels Ryberg, 1860-1904. Letters, 1904, (3 items) (Box 4)
    Letters from Niels R. Finsen, the 1903 Nobel Prize awardee for Medicine or Physiology. Envelope addressed to Hr. Docent Dr. phil.Schmidt-Nielsen, Lysintituts Laboratorium, Rosenvaenget, [Köbenhaven]. Typescript transcription of the Danish text and English translation.
  - Fiquet. Letter, 1816 Apr. 15, (1 item) (Box 4)
    Identifies himself as "ex-director of the department of 'mendicité,'" which was essentially a poorhouse. Writes from Caen, France. Mentions Paris and mentions sleepwalking multiple times, a possible political metaphor or else discussion of the actual phenomenon. A modern note in the folder states that the recipient was a Matthieu-Guillaume-Thérèse Villenave (1762-1846), an editor and literary figure.
  - Fish, Henry. Papers, 1819-1846, (23 items) (Box 5)
    Physician of Salisbury. Holograph documents, a few signed. Account statements and receipts of payments for medical services, advice and medicine, rendered to the town of Salisbury by Dr. Henry Fish.
  - Fisher, Alexander. Letter, 1821, Jan. 6, (1 item) (Box 5)
    British astronomer and Artic explorer, sometimes listed as George Fisher. Letter (ALS). Fisher writes of his journal, presumably of the expedition of the H.M.S. Dorothea and Trent in 1818, and of the publication of Parry's account of the same. He writes of a future expedition, aboard the H.M.S. Hecla.
  - Fiveroke, Peter. Ledger, 1791-1792, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Ledger of sums owed to Fiveroke by Christian Forny for various medical supplies and services. The account is witnessed and signed by Jacob Young, a Justice of the Peace for Frederick County, November 20, 1793.
  - Flint, Austin, 1812-1886. Note, 1882, Jan. 30, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Physician of New York. Note (ANS). Asks the addressee to make a house call.
  - Flourens, Pierre, 1794-1867. Papers, 1851-1857, (6 items) (Box 5)
    French physiologist. DS and a letter (ALS). Notices, signed by Flourens, acknowledging receipt of materials sent by M. Vattemare, Mr. Macculloch, and A. D. Bache. He also writes to M. Sauve regarding the eulogy of M. Leruy.
  - Foot, Jesse, 1744-1826. Papers, 1810-1826, (7 items) (Box 5)
    English surgeon. Letters (ALS). Correspondence from Jesse Foot and his nephew, Jesse Foot, Jr., who succeeded him in his practice, to the publishers and printers John Nichols (1745-1826) and his son John Bowyer Nichols (1779-1863), relating to the publication of Foot's work. Foot, Jr., informs Nichols of his uncle's death. In a pair of letters Foot inquires into the date of birth of William Johnstone Strathmore.
  - Forwood, William Stump, 1830-1892. Papers, 1857-1863, (71 items) (Box 5)
    Maryland physician and ethnologist. Letters (ALS). William Stump Forwood was a Maryland physician who attempted to justify slavery on medical grounds. This body of correspondence, almost exclusively letters to Forwood and written immediately before and during the early part of the Civil War, relates to questions of race, e.g. "the Negro problem", intermarriage and consanguinity. The mechanics of editing and publishing a medical journal also form a topic of discussion. Principal correspondents are Samuel Worcester Butler and Washington Chew Van Bibber. Other correspondents are Sylvester David Willard, John H. Van Evrie, J. P. Evans, Joseph Leidy, S. M. Bemiss, James A. Bayard, and Samuel A. Cartwright. Additional Forwood papers are held by UNC-Chapel Hill (1600 items).
  - Fothergill, John, 1712-1780. Papers, 1755, (2 items) (Box 5)
    Quaker physician, botanist and natural philosopher. Letters (ALS). Fothergill comments upon a volume sent him by Emanual Mendez da Costa, foreign secretary of the Royal Society of London. Da Costa writes in reply. His letter bears no signature.
  - Foucault, Jean Bernard Léon, 1819-1868. Note, 1851, Aug. 24, (1 item) (Box 5)
    French physicist who demonstrated the diurnal motion of the earth by pendulum. Note (ANS). Assures M. Lormier that things are in good hands.
  - Fourier, Jean Baptiste Joseph, Baron, 1768-1830. Papers, 1851 and undated, (3 items) (Box 5)
    French chemist. Autograph note, signed; autograph note, unsigned, attached to holograph document, signed, dated 1851, which bears several signed notes in the margins.
  - Fraenkel, Ludwig, b. 1870. Letter, 1924, Jan. 26, (1 item) (Box 5)
    German obstetrician and gynecologist. Letter (TLS). Informs addressee of the program for an upcoming meeting.
  - Francis, John Wakefield, 1789-1861. Letter, 1853, Dec. 20, (1 item) (Box 5)
    New York physician. Letter (ALS). Welcomes Dr. O'Callaghan's "Documentary history of New York", sent to him by Randall, as a fitting tribute to the greatness of the state and mentions his own part in promoting work on the Erie Canal.
  - Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790. Letter, 1766, Dec. 20, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Letter (ALS). Introduces Benjamin Rush and Jonathan Potts. Refers to inquiries into Swinton's lands in New Jersey, made on his behalf by Franklin's son, William, then Governor of New Jersey.
  - Freeland, James, 1743-1796. Papers, 1781-1790, (18 items) (Box 5)
    Physician of Hopkinton, R. I. and Sutton, Mass. Holograph documents, signed. Promissory notes, some of which are also signed by Joseph Elliot, and a bill of sale of land. Two typed biographical notes.
  - French miscellaneous autographs, 1829 and undated, (3 items) (Box 5)
    Three manuscript pages from unknown sources, two of which contain signatures of professors and physicians. One page carries as title, "Professeurs présens à la Séance du [24?] Juillet 1829." The third page seems to be a list of names rather than individual signatures.
  - Frerichs, Friedrich Theodor, 1819-1885. Note, 1875, (1 item) (Box 5)
    German clinician and pathological anatomist. Note (ANS).
  - Fry, Elizabeth Gurney, 1780-1845. Papers, 1821-1842, (3 items) (Box 5)
    English Quaker, prison reformer and philanthropist. Letters (ALS). A joint letter from Fry and her brother, Joseph, thanks James Williams, sheriff of London and Middlesex, for his interest in and support of the work of their organization for the improvement of female prisoners at Newgate. In the other letters, Fry briefly refers to her opinion on separate confinement and the new colony at Australsund in West Australia.
  - Gage, Homer, 1861-1938. Letter, 1919, Nov., 21, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Massachusetts surgeon. Letter (ALS). Responding to an inquiry by Pleadwell, as related by the recipient of the letter, Gage discusses the Legion, an organization for medical men who served in the army during the war.
  - Gannett, Caleb, 1745-1818. Letter, 1781, Apr. 20, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Minister and tutor in mathematics and philsophy at Harvard College until 1780. Secretary of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Letter (ALS). Gannett consults Cotton Tufts (1734-1815), a physician, founder of the Academy, and cousin of John Adams, about a "disorder called defluction form the lungs".
  - Gardiner, Silvester, 1708-1786. Papers, 1767-1785, (3 items) (Box 5)
    Loyalist and Boston physician and landowner. Letters (ALS) relating to financial matters.
  - Garretson, James Edmund, 1828-1895. Letter, 1881, Oct. 10, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Dentist and oral surgeon of Philadelphia. Letter (ALS). Informs Knortz that copies of the books, "Thinkers and thinking" and "Two thousand years after", have been sent. Congratulates him on presenting William Cullen Bryant. Knortz introduced much North American history and literature to a German-speaking audience.
  - Garrison, Fielding Hudson, 1870-1935. Letters, 1917, 1928, (2 items) (Box 5)
    Medical librarian and historian of medicine. Letters (ALS). Writes of George Jackson Fisher as a pioneer in medical history. Responds to Friedrich Schiller Lee's (U.S. physician) inquiries after English and/or German translations of the Mount Ebers Papyrus.
  - Gerbier, Humbert. Document, 1792, Feb. 4, (1 item) (Box 5)
    French physician and member of the American Philosophical Society. Autograph document, signed. Attests that poor health prevents Charles Curain and his wife Marguerite from earning their living.
  - Gibbes, Robert Wilson, 1809-1866. Document, 1851 and undated, (3 items) (Box 5)
    Physician and chemist of Charleston and Columbia, S. C. Letters (ALS). Joseph Leidy writes regarding the prices of various anatomical preparations; Samuel George Morton sends a book with an autograph of J. Locke; and John Edwards Holbrook inquires whether the library owns a particular volume of the "Transactions of the Academy of Arts and Sciences of Boston".
  - Gibson, William, 1788-1868. Papers, 1826, (2 items) (Box 5)
    Surgeon of Philadelphia. Letters (ALS) of recommendation for Andrew E. Kennedy and William Wilson.
  - Gilbert, David, 1803-1868. Letter, 1859, Sept. 17, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Surgeon of Philadelphia. Letter (ALS). Writes on the use and types of adhesive plaster.
  - Gilbert, Ludwig Wilhelm, 1769-1824. Letter, 1809, Feb. 22, (1 item) (Box 5)
    German physicist and chemist. Letter (ALS). A plea, on behalf of his mother and other pensioners, for the back payment of their pensions.
  - Ginsberg, Louis, 1895-1976. Papers, 1958-1968, (15 items) (Box 5)
    Correspondence concerning Louis Ginsberg's bookplate collection, 1958-1968.
  - Girard, Jean, 1770-1852. Letter, 1814, Sept. 17, (1 item) (Box 5)
    French veterinarian. Letter (ALS). A cordial personal letter.
  - Giraudy, Charles François Simon, 1770-1848. Letter, [Between 1800 and 1848], (1 item) (Box 5)
    French psychiatrist of Charenton. Letter (ALS) relating medical notes and observations.
  - Glentworth, Thomas. Document, 1738 or 1739, Jan. 26, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Physician of Philadelphia and father of George Glentworth, senior surgeon in the Continental Army. Autograph document, signed. Certifies receipt of one pound ten shilling from Mr. John Reynall.
  - Goiffon, Jean Baptiste, 1658-1730. Manuscript, 1716, June 29, (1 item) (Box 5)
    French physician of Lyon. Manuscript, signed. Writes on diseases of the stomach.
  - Good, John Mason, 1764-1827. Papers, [Between 1784 and 1827], (2 items) (Box 5)
    English physician and author of a number of works of medicine and natural history. Letters (ALS). Writes to Mr. J. Robinson and Mr. Stockdale respectively regarding his account and the sale of his work.
  - Good, Samuel. Certificate, 1844, Aug. 26, (1 item) (Box 5)
    Certificate of admittance as Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons of England.
  - Goodhue, Edward Solon, 1863-1935. Papers, 1900-1909 and undated, (11 items) (Box 5)